Finding aid to the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00535
Sophia Smith Collection
- Rosario Morales interviewed by Kelly Anderson, January 29-30, 2005; Morales, Rosario, 1930-; Anderson, Kelly (Box 35)
  In this oral history Morales discusses her family background and childhood in New York City, discovering radical politics, and her work as a writer and poet. Morales details her experience within the Communist Party, both in New York and in Puerto Rico, and her developing feminist consciousness. She speaks to the roles of women in the Party, the Left in general, and in the academy. Morales is forthcoming about her relationships with her husband and children, particularly her daughter (and co-author) Aurora. Her work as a writer and poet is the predominant theme of the latter half of the interview. (Transcript 78 pp.)
- Marjory Nelson interviewed by Kate Weigand, May 18-19, 2005; Nelson, Marjory; Weigand, Kate (Box 36)
  Marjory Nelson (b. 1928) grew up in New Brunswick, NJ. She married at age 19 and defined herself primarily as a wife and mother for the next 20 years. Inspired by Betty Friedan's The Feminine Mystique, Nelson returned to college in the mid-1960s and began to participate in the radical political movements of that decade. She graduated from the University of Akron with a B.A. in 1966 and an M.A. in Social Psychology in 1968. She was awarded a Ph.D. in Sociology from the State University of New York at Buffalo in 1976, having completed a dissertation which examined the National Woman's Party. She was instrumental in the founding of Women's Studies at both SUNY-Buffalo and at Antioch College in Ohio. Nelson has been involved in peace, civil rights, feminist, and lesbian activism; her most notable political activities include lobbying for the ERA in Congress, organizing to free Joann Little and the Wilmington Ten, and co-founding the Women's Building in San Francisco. Her articles and essays have appeared in a wide variety of feminist publications including Sinister Wisdom, Sojourner, and off our backs. Since the 1980s Nelson has lived in San Francisco where she works as a hypnotherapist and a lesbian feminist activist.
  In this oral history Marjory Nelson describes her childhood in the 1930s and 1940s in an upper middle-class academic family in New Brunswick, NJ, her life as a typical white suburban housewife and mother in the 1950s and 1960s, her transformation into a middle-aged white academic feminist and leftist political activist after 1968, and her experiences as a lesbian activist living and working in San Francisco since the late 1970s. The interview focuses on Nelson's transformation from married housewife to activist academic, her work with the National Woman's Party and its founder Alice Paul, her personal and political relationship with old left lawyer Mary Kaufman, her involvement in interracial feminist organizing in the 1970s, and her work as a lesbian activist in California since the 1980s. Nelson's story details the ways the social and political upheavals of the 1960s and 1970s, especially the second wave of the women's movement, changed many women's lives. It also illustrates important connections between feminism and a variety of other twentieth century movements for social change. (Transcript 89 pp.)
  The Marjory Nelson Papers are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Karen Nussbaum interviewed by Kathleen Banks Nutter, December 18-19, 2003; Nussbaum, Karen, 1950-; Nutter, Kathleen Banks (Box 37)
  Karen Nussbaum was born in Chicago April 25, 1950, the daughter of Annette Brenner Nussbaum, who "did public relations for educational institutions and organizations for the public good for many years," and Mike (Myron) Nussbaum, an exterminator (1946-70) and actor and director (1967-present). She attended the University Chicago for a year and a half and became involved in the anti-Vietnam War movement. She moved to Boston, working for the antiwar movement there while supporting herself as a clerical worker at Harvard University. She earned a B.A. from Goddard College in 1975.
  In 1973 Nussbaum and some friends organized 9to5, an organization for women clerical workers, initially in Boston. By 1975, Boston 9to5 had joined other similar groups across the country and they reached out to a mostly unreceptive labor movement. SEIU, however, welcomed them and Local 925 was born. In 1981 the union expanded to a national jurisdiction and became SEIU District 925. Nussbaum was president of the 925 union and executive director of 9to5 until 1993. In 1993 President Bill Clinton appointed her as director of the Women's Bureau of the U.S. Department of Labor. In 1996 she went to the AFL-CIO to head up the newly created Working Women's Department, which was phased out in 2001. Since then, Nussbaum has served as Assistant to the President of the AFL-CIO, John Sweeney, and as director of Working America, community affiliate of the AFL-CIO. She lives in Washington, D.C., with her husband and their three children, who range in age from 15 to 20.
  The oral history focuses on the various phases of Nussbaum's life but is especially strong on her role as a co-founder of 9to5 and her work on behalf of working women, both as a government official and within the trade union movement. (Transcript 55 pp.)
- LaDoris Payne interviewed by Martha Ackelsberg, April 10-11, 2005; Payne, LaDoris, 1948; Ackelsberg, Martha (Box 38)
  LaDoris Payne (b. 1948) was born and raised in St. Louis, Missouri, and has spent much of her life there. She is currently director of the Imani Family Center, which was established in 1993 and is located in a former Ursuline convent. She also directs WomanSpirit in St. Louis, an organization formed in 1984 to provide a place for women to gather, talk, and support one another in their struggles against poverty. WomanSpirit has received funding from a variety of organizations and foundations that have enabled it to develop programs such as Enterprising Women, a microenterprise training program; the Imani Business Incubator and Technology Center; and the House of David shelter, a transitional home for homeless disabled veterans. Payne has been affiliated with the National Congress of Neighborhood Women (NCNW) and with GROOTS (Grassroots Organizations Operating Together in Sisterhood) since the early 1990's. She served as a delegate to the United Nations 4th World Conference on Women in 1995 in Beijing, to the UN Conference on Sustainable Environments in 1996; and to the UN/Economic Commission for Europe preparatory meeting on the 2000 review of the implementation of the Beijing Platform for Action. In 1994, on the 10th anniversary of WomanSpirit, Inc., the mayor of St. Louis declared WomanSpirit Day in St. Louis, and LaDoris was also named the Homeless Service Provider of the Year for her work in opening the House of David shelter.
  The interview provides a wealth of information on LaDoris Payne's growing up in segregated St. Louis, MO, the relationships within and among her family, her struggles with illness and depression, and, ultimately, her coming into her own as an activist and organizer. It is rich in discussion of both the strengths of the black community in St. Louis before Brown v. Board of Education and the personal costs to those children who, like LaDoris, were among the first to go to integrated schools. The oral history gives a sense of her own personal trajectory as an activist, of the ways she was able to use government programs (e.g. War on Poverty programs) to pull herself out of poverty; and, most dramatically, of the vision and energy that have gone into the establishment of WomanSpirit, the Imani Family Center, and David's House. There is also considerable information about her engagement with the National Congress of Neighborhood Women and GROOTS, as well as with UN-related and other international organizations whose meetings she has attended. (Transcript 68 pp.)
  The National Congress of Neighborhood Women Records are available for research at Smith College Special Collections. Another oral history of Payne is in the New York City Women Community Activists Oral History Project.
- Jan Peterson interviewed by Martha Ackelsberg, January 23-24, 2006; Peterson, Jan; Ackelsberg, Martha A. (Box 39)
  Researchers must have permission from Peterson to access this interview. Please contact Smith College Special Collections for information about securing access permissions.
  Born in South Milwaukee, Wisconsin, in 1941, Jan (Janice) Peterson is a long-time organizer of neighborhood-based, grassroots, working-class women's organizations. She founded the National Congress of Neighborhood Women in 1974 and GROOTS (Grassroots Women Organizing Together in Sisterhood) in 1989, and she is a prime mover of the Huairou Commission. Peterson is a creative, charismatic, and forceful leader who has managed to bridge what often appear to be not only gaps, but abysses, between neighborhood women and foundations, working-class and middle-class women's organizations, ethnic women and feminist organizations, and the like.
  Peterson lived in the Milwaukee area through high school and graduated from the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 1963. She spent the following year (1963-64) in New York City, where she became involved with CORE (the Congress of Racial Equality). After a brief time in Wisconsin in 1964, she returned to New York in 1966, where she became involved in Mobilization for Youth. In 1969, she moved to Williamsburg, Brooklyn, where she began the work that eventually resulted in the founding of the National Congress of Neighborhood Women (NCNW). During those years Peterson was also involved with the women's movement in New York City, including NOW, the October 17th group, and New York Radical Feminists. In 1977, she went to Washington, D.C., serving as an assistant to Midge Costanza in the Carter White House. Since the 1980s, Peterson has been involved in a variety of community-based and women's community development organizations, and has increasingly moved into the international arena, becoming active in UN and UN-related organizations. She is now helping to steer the organizations that remain affiliated with the NCNW into a network of "living-learning centers."
  This interview is particularly rich in describing Peterson's involvement with the multiple social movements of the 1960s and 1970s that profoundly altered her life and the lives of many of her generation-especially the civil rights, welfare rights, and women's movements in New York City. It demonstrates the ways her involvement with each affected the others, and the close-often profoundly painful-connections and tensions between the "personal" and the "political" that roiled those movements during those years. The oral history also contains fascinating and detailed reflections on her own growth as an organizer, on the meanings of politics and democracy, on the difficulties of organizing as the larger political context and funding opportunities changed, and on the difficulties-and the opportunities-offered by working in groups that consistently attempt to bridge differences, of race, ethnicity, and class. (Transcript 148 pp.)
  The National Congress of Neighborhood Women Records are available for research at Smith College Special Collections. Another oral history of Peterson is in the New York City Women Community Activists Oral History Project.
- Suzanne Pharr interviewed by Kelly Anderson, June 28-29, 2005; Pharr, Suzanne, 1939-; Anderson, Kelly (Box 40)
  The youngest of eight children, Suzanne Pharr (b. 1939) was raised in Lawrenceville, GA. A self-described "white, queer, southern, anti-racist worker," Pharr has been a social justice organizer since the 1960s. She was the editor of the women's newspaper Distaff, co-founder of the first domestic violence shelter in Arkansas, and founder of the Women's Project in Little Rock, AR. Pharr was the first female executive director of the Highlander Research and Education Center.
  In addition to her organizing work, Pharr is an accomplished public intellectual and writer. She is the author of two books: In the Time of the Right: Reflections on Liberation (1996) and Homophobia: A Weapon of Sexism (1988). She currently resides in Knoxville, TN, and is working on a new project with Southerners on New Ground.
  In this oral history Pharr recalls her childhood in Hog Mountain, Georgia. She explores the nuances of class, race and gender in white rural and working-class communities across the South. Pharr describes her introduction to the civil rights movement during college and her discovery of the women's movement and lesbian community. Her interview is particularly strong on the connections between anti-racist and feminist work, the anti-violence movement, and the politics of sexuality within the women's movement. (Transcript 81 pp.)
- Setsuko (Suki) Terada Ports interviewed by Loretta J. Ross, January 5, 2008; Ports, Suki Terada; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 41)
  Setsuko ("Suki") Terada Ports was born December 12, 1934, in New York City. Her mother, Sumiko Takai, had immigrated from Japan to the US as a child with her family. Her father, Yoshio (Albert) Terada, was born in Hawaii; he owned a gift shop in New York City that catered to a Japanese clientele. Both were college graduates.
  Suki grew up and has lived most of her life in the Morningside Park neighborhood of Harlem. She attended the Horace Mann-Lincoln School (lab school of Teachers College at Columbia University) and the High School of Music and Art, and graduated from the New Lincoln School. After graduating from Smith College as an education major in 1956, she taught for a year in Turkey, where she met her husband, Horace Gonder Ports, Jr. Their marriage in 1958 generated considerable racial hostility from her white in-laws. Her husband died in 1971 at the age of 36, leaving her a single mother of three. She held a series of short-term jobs in the 1970s.
  Ports' community-based activism began in the 1960s with engagement in local educational issues and struggles over the neighborhood park and access to public space. Since the 1980s she has focused her energies on HIV/AIDS and on the needs of low-income AIDS patients with the least access to health care and social services: people of color, women, drug addicts. She created the Minority Task Force on AIDS under the auspices of the Council of Churches in 1985 and was a co-founder of the National Minority AIDS Council in 1986. In 1989 she founded the Family Health Project to focus on issues of women of color and AIDS.
  Ports has served on the boards of numerous organizations, including Asian Americans for Equality, the New York Women's Foundation, and Asian Pacific Islander Women's HIV/AIDS Network, the National Minority AIDS Council, the Sister Fund, and the Japanese American Association of New York. She has consulted to multiple projects targeting race, class, and gender inequities in health care, and she is the recipient of numerous awards, including the Susan B. Anthony Award of the NYC chapter of the National Organization for Women, the Frederick Douglass Award of the North Star.
  Ports recalls vivid stories of the impact of FBI surveillance of her family during World War II, including her mother's house arrest. She describes growing up in a Japanese American family in the postwar years. She details racial tensions in her personal life and public work, and comments on cultural norms and stereotypes that have influenced her ability to speak out. Ports summarizes her years of organizing around AIDS.(Transcript 91 pp.)
- Achebe Betty Powell interviewed by Kelly Anderson, July 6-7, 2004; Powell, Achebe Betty, 1940-; Anderson, Kelly (Box 42)
  Achebe Betty Powell (b.1940) was raised in Florida, graduated with a B.A. from The College of St. Catherine and an M.A. in French Language and Literature from Fordham University, and has resided in New York City for the past 40 years. Powell has been an activist since high school, when she joined the National Conference of Christians and Jews. Powell was a self-possessed and mature young woman - from her activism, to living abroad with her father, to being one of the only black students at a Midwestern Catholic women's college. As an adult, Powell was poised to take leadership in many liberation struggles. Powell was a key player in the Gay Academic Union, the National Black Feminist Organization, and the National Gay Task Force. She was a founding member of Salsa Soul Sisters and the Astraea Foundation. Powell has been a professor at Brooklyn College, a social worker, and an employee at Kitchen Table Press before she went on to diversity and anti-racism training, work which has taken her around the globe in the struggle for human rights and liberation. She currently resides in Brooklyn, NY.
  In this oral history Powell describes her extended family network and roots in the African-Methodist-Episcopal church. She details living in Germany with her father in the 1950s, her conversion to Catholicism, and attending college in St. Paul, MN. Powell recounts her introduction to activism through the National Council of Christians and Jews, and the climate of racism and anti-Semitism in the mid-century South. Powell describes her coming out-both politically and sexually-during the 1970s, into both the gay and lesbian and feminist movements. She recounts her affiliations with the Gay Academic Union, the National Gay Task Force, the National Black Feminist Organization, Salsa Soul Sisters, Kitchen Table Press, and the Astraea Foundation, shedding new light on the politics of race, class, sex, and sexuality. Powell also describes the origins of her international feminist work and Betty Powell Associates, Powell's consulting and training agency which does organizational development work with a focus on anti-oppression diversity. An epilogue regarding Powell's name change - from Betty Jean Powell, when the interview took place, to Achebe Betty Powell - follows the transcript. (Transcript 86 pp.)
- Minnie Bruce Pratt interviewed by Kelly Anderson, March 16-17, 2005; Pratt, Minnie Bruce; Anderson, Kelly (Box 43)
  Born in Selma, Alabama, in 1946, Minnie Bruce Pratt is an award-winning poet, essayist, teacher and activist. She graduated from the University of Alabama in 1968 and received a Ph.D. in English Literature from the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, in 1979. Pratt found the women's movement in 1974, while living in Fayetteville, North Carolina, and began a new life as an out lesbian, a feminist, a writer, and an activist. Pratt was a member of the editorial collective Feminary, worked with the National Organization for Women and with the local rape crisis line and women's center, sat on the Cumberland County Council on the Status of Women, and co-founded WomanWrites: A Southeastern Lesbian Writers Conference and LIPS, a lesbian direct-action group. Pratt's engagement with feminism and antiracism is best known through her cultural activism. Her publications are extensive and include Yours in Struggle: Three Feminist Perspectives on Anti-Semitism and Racism, with Elly Bulkin and Barbara Smith (1984); Crime Against Nature (1990); Rebellion (1991); and S/He (1995). For the past ten years, Pratt's activism has been in connection with the International Action Center, the Workers World Party, and the transgender movement. She lives with her partner Leslie Feinberg in Jersey City, New Jersey.
  In this oral history, Pratt describes her Southern heritage and family background. She reflects on her marriage, its dissolution, and the loss of custody of her children. Pratt describes a distinctly Southern women's movement in the 1970s, offering important insights into the dynamics of race and racism and the politics of sexuality, and discusses in depth the Feminary collective. The interview focuses on Pratt's activism as a writer, the development of her antiracist and anti-imperialist consciousness, and her identity as a femme. (Transcript 102 pp.)
- Patricia Reeve interviewed by Kathleen Banks Nutter, November 21, 2003; Reeve, Patricia, 1953-; Nutter, Kathleen Banks (Box 44)
  Patricia Reeve was born in Akron, Ohio, in 1953, the daughter of a chemical engineer/lawyer father and an Italian immigrant mother who "broke with family tradition" by attending nursing school and continued working as a nurse until Pat was in grade school (by then she had three younger siblings). She was raised by "devout Catholics" and is also the great niece of socialist, suffragist, and labor organizer Ella Reeve Bloor. While Pat was a sophomore in high school, her mother died; until her father remarried a year later, Pat "assumed responsibility for the household." She graduated from Northern Illinois University (B.A., History, 1975; M.A., History, 1978).
  After several clerical and retail positions, Reeve joined 9to5 as an organizer in 1979, working in the Boston area until 1985. Thereafter she joined the faculty at the Labor Studies Program, University of Massachusetts, Boston, working primarily with non-traditional students. From 1997-2003, she was director of the Labor Resource Center at University of Massachusetts, Boston, where she coordinated the labor education program. She was a co-founder of WILD (the Women's Institute for Leadership Development) in 1986 and remains on their board today; she is also active in the Gay and Lesbian Labor Activists Network. She and her partner, Debby Briggs, adopted a special-needs child in 1996: today Laurie is a thriving thirteen-year-old. Reeve recently earned a Ph.D. at Boston College.
  The oral history focuses on the various phases of Reeve's life but is especially strong on her union activities and her career as a labor educator. (Transcript 62 pp.)
  The Ella Reeve Bloor Papers are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Luz Rodriguez interviewed by Joyce Follet, June 16-17, 2006; Rodriguez, Luz, 1956-; Follet, Joyce (Box 45)
  Luz Marina Rodriquez was born in New York City on March 7, 1956, and grew up on the Lower East Side. She was the eldest of three children of Elsa Rodriguez Vazquez and Luis Rodriguez Nieto, Sr., who had both recently migrated from Puerto Rico as part of Operation Bootstrap. Her father held a variety of jobs, including electronics repair and night security work, while her mother worked as an Avon Lady.
  After graduating from Seward Park High School in 1974, Rodriguez spent two years immersed in social and cultural activities in her Puerto Rican neighborhood, which became known as Loisaida. She was deeply involved in The Real Great Society, a gang outreach and community empowerment organization created in 1964 to engage youth in addressing local needs, especially sweat equity projects to create affordable housing. She was also an active participant in CHARAS/El Bohio, a cultural center where she taught Puerto Rican folkloric dance.
  After studying dance at Pratt Institute, Rodriguez graduated from NYU as a dance therapy major in 1982. College research into the sterilization and birth control experimentation on Puerto Rican women planted the seed of later reproductive rights activism.